

<topic
  name     = "Welcome!"
  triggers = "checkShowWelcome"
  urgent   = "true"
>
  <image>media/Help/start_banner.png</image>
  <content>Hello, and welcome to Stratos: The Sci-Fi Settlement Sim!  This tutorial will walk you through the essentials of setting up a settlement, exploring the surrounds, dealing with potential threats, and establishing a sound economy.</content>
  <link name="Navigation">Continue</link>
</topic>


<topic
  name      = "Navigation"
  urgent    = "true"
  completes = "checkMotionDone"
>
  <content>First, you'll need to familiarise yourself with basic controls.  Use the W, S, A and D keys to move your viewpoint forward, back, left or right.

(Note:  You can also use the arrow keys, click on the ground, or click a position on the minimap in the top-left.)</content>
</topic>


<topic
  name     = "Navigation Done"
  urgent   = "true"
  triggers = "checkMotionDone"
  whenOpen = "whenMotionDone"
>
  <content>Well done!  If you ever get lost, messages (such as this one) can always be accessed from the Messages listing on the left-hand side of the screen.</content>
  <link name="The Bastion">Continue</link>
</topic>


<topic
  name     = "The Bastion"
  whenOpen = "whenBastionTopicOpen"
>
  <content>Your settlement starts out with a single main building:  The Bastion, which houses your family and personal servants, and serves as your seat of command for the settlement as a whole.  As such, you should strive to protect the Bastion at all costs.

To do this, you will need to both identify any threats in the area, and take steps to establish defences, which is what we'll cover next.</content>
  <link name="Place a Trooper Lodge">Continue</link>
</topic>




<topic
  name      = "Place a Trooper Lodge"
  urgent    = "true"
  whenOpen  = "whenPlaceBarracksRequestOpen"
  completes = "checkBarracksPlaced"
  onFinish  = "onBarracksPlaced"
>
  <content>To hire troops and other personnel, you'll need to construct facilities to house them.

Open the Installations tab in the top-right of the screen.  Select the Trooper Lodge, click build, and then place one next to your Bastion.</content>
</topic>


<topic
  name     = "Trooper Lodge Placed"
  urgent   = "true"
  triggers = "checkBarracksPlaced"
>
  <content>Good work.  Normally, buildings will take a while to construct and fully staff, but for now we'll speed things up and provide some starting recruits.  If you like, you can click on the new building and take a look at the staff recruited.

Your citizens cannot be directly controlled, but you can hire them to perform missions on your behalf.  Next, we'll engage some of your troops to explore the surrounds of your base.</content>
  <link name="Declare a Recon Mission">Continue</link>
</topic>


<topic
  name      = "Declare a Recon Mission"
  urgent    = "true"
  whenOpen  = "whenExploreRequestOpen"
  completes = "checkExploreBegun"
  onFinish  = "onExploreBegun"
>
  <content>Click on a darkened area of the map, and a small green icon should appear in the lower-centre of the screen.  Press this to declare a Recon Mission.</content>
</topic>


<topic
  name     = "Recon Mission Begun"
  urgent   = "true"
  triggers = "checkExploreBegun"
>
  <content>Good work.  We'll assign some of your staff to the Recon Mission, but you can adjust the reward offered to attract more applicants.

Your troopers should begin exploring the assigned area shortly.  In the meanwhile, let's take a look at getting a basic economy up and running.</content>
  <link name="Economy Basics">Continue</link>
</topic>




<topic
  name      = "Economy Basics"
  urgent    = "true"
  whenOpen  = "whenPlaceFacilitiesRequestOpen"
  completes = "checkFacilitiesPlaced"
  onFinish  = "onFacilitiesPlaced"
>
  <content>Go the the Installations panel again, and place a Supply Depot (under Commerce structures) and Engineer Station (under Engineer structures) close to your Bastion.</content>
</topic>


<topic
  name      = "Facilities Placed"
  urgent    = "true"
  triggers  = "checkFacilitiesPlaced"
  completes = "checkFacilitiesReady"
  onFinish  = "onFacilitiesReady"
>
  <content>Excellent.  The technicians at your Bastion should now begin constructing these facilities.  Once that's complete, we'll provide some initial staff and move on to getting some cash flow going.</content>
</topic>


<topic
  name      = "Install Upgrades"
  urgent    = "true"
  triggers  = "checkFacilitiesReady"
  completes = "checkUpgradesReady"
>
  <content>Good work.

To improve their production of goods and range of services, many buildings can have upgrades installed.

Select the Engineer Station, open the Upgrades pane, and queue Assembly Line three times.  Your construction staff will attend to it shortly, speeding up Parts manufacture.  These can then be sold for a profit.</content>
</topic>


<topic
  name      = "Change Trade Settings"
  urgent    = "true"
  triggers  = "checkUpgradesReady"
  completes = "checkTradeSetup"
  onFinish  = "onTradeSetup"
>
  <content>You can also modify the trade settings at your Supply Depot.  Select the Supply Depot, open the Stock pane, and increase your imports of Metals to 10 and exports of Parts to 20.</content>
</topic>


<topic
  name     = "Trade Setup Done"
  urgent   = "true"
  triggers = "checkTradeSetup"
>
  <content>That should do it.  It takes a little time for dropships to arrive and perform their transactions- typically once per day.

Once a sale is complete, on-duty auditors from your Bastion will drop by to record and file your profits and losses.  The trick is to make sure you have more of the former.

In the meantime, let's take another look at base security.</content>
  <link name="Destroy The Nearby Ruins">Continue</link>
</topic>





<topic
  name      = "Destroy The Nearby Ruins"
  urgent    = "true"
  whenOpen  = "whenNearRuinsTopicOpen"
  completes = "checkAttackMissionSetup"
  onFinish  = "onAttackMissionSetup"
>
  <content>This is an Ancient Ruin close to your base.  Structures such as these often harbour dangerous creatures who may assault your base and waylay colonists- as such, it's a good idea to raze them when found.

Select the Ancient Ruin and declare a Strike Mission (the small red icon underneath.)  Then increase the reward high enough to attract applicants to carry out the job.</content>
</topic>


<topic
  name      = "Strike Mission Begun"
  urgent    = "true"
  triggers  = "checkAttackMissionSetup"
  completes = "checkNearRuinsDronesDestroyed"
>
  <content>Now that you have some applicants for the Strike Mission, they should polish off the ruins in short order.  Take care, however- some of the inhabitants will defend themselves!</content>
</topic>


<topic
  name      = "Drones Destroyed"
  urgent    = "true"
  triggers  = "checkNearRuinsDronesDestroyed"
  completes = "checkNearRuinsDestroyed"
>
  <content>Now that any local resistance has been dealt with, the ruins should fall in short order.</content>
</topic>


<topic
  name      = "Strike Mission Complete"
  urgent    = "true"
  triggers  = "checkNearRuinsDestroyed"
>
  <content>Excellent!  Now that the ruins are destroyed, let's return to base.</content>
  <link name="Hiring Basics">Continue</link>
</topic>


<topic
  name      = "Hiring Basics"
  urgent    = "true"
  whenOpen  = "whenHiringBasicsTopicOpen"
  completes = "checkHiringDone"
>
  <content>A number of veterans Troopers have applied to work at your Trooper Lodge, but you don't have space for all of them.  Open the facility's Staff tab- or the Personnel pane- to view their skills and traits.  Then you can decide which to hire.</content>
</topic>


<topic
  name      = "Troops Hired"
  urgent    = "true"
  triggers = "checkHiringDone"
>
  <content>That's it.  Fresh recruits will arrive aboard visiting Dropships, along with trade goods.  But they might not arrive for a while.  If you like, you can open the facility's Staffing tab to get an ETA.

While we're waiting, let's take a fresh look at our cash flow.</content>
  <link name="Profits and Loss">Continue</link>
</topic>





<topic
  name      = "Profits and Loss"
  urgent    = "true"
  whenOpen  = "whenBudgetsTopicOpen"
  completes = "checkBudgetsPaneOpened"
>
  <content>At the moment, your funds are likely to be running low.  We'll explore some methods of fixing that, but first you should open the Finance pane (first button in the top-right), and click on the Budgets tab.  Then you can take a look at your profits and losses for each day.</content>
</topic>

<topic
  name      = "Expanding Industry"
  urgent    = "true"
  triggers  = "checkBudgetsPaneOpened"
  whenOpen  = "whenExpandingIndustryTopicOpen"
  completes = "checkExtraIndustryPlaced"
>
  <content>...Not too encouraging.

There are many ways to earn credits, but on a map like this, with large areas of barren rock and irradiated wasteland, heavy industry can turn a fast profit.  Place a second Engineer Station near your first, and an Excavation Site somewhere close to both.

Mining is most efficient near outcrops of surface rock, so keep an eye out for those, or check the minerals overlay on the minimap.</content>
</topic>

<topic
  name      = "Personal Housing"
  urgent    = "true"
  triggers  = "checkExtraIndustryPlaced"
  whenOpen  = "whenPersonalHousingTopicOpen"
  completes = "checkHousingPlaced"
>
  <content>While those are building, you may also want to start thinking about giving your citizens a few amenities, such as private housing.  Your colonists will claim lots by themselves given time and space, but you can anticipate that by placing a Seal Tent or two in convenient locations.</content>
</topic>

<topic
  name      = "Build a Stock Exchange"
  urgent    = "true"
  triggers  = "checkHousingPlaced"
  whenOpen  = "whenStockExchangeTopicOpen"
  completes = "checkStockExchangePlaced"
>
  <content>Finally, your citizens will eventually want food.  For now, the simplest solution is to build a Stock Exchange nearby- this will import carbs and protein, along with other goods, and sell it to local homesteaders at a profit.</content>
</topic>

<topic
  name      = "Time and Money"
  urgent    = "true"
  triggers  = "checkStockExchangePlaced"
>
  <content>Housing yields tax income, and will upgrade itself as more goods and services become available.  The Stock Exchange also boosts profits from trade.

Between imports and hiring, it might take a few days for your industry and trade venues to start turning a profit, however.  Check on your citizens from time to time- particularly the Auditors at your Bastion- along with your Finances pane, to see where the money is going.

In the meantime, when and if you're ready, we'll turn our attentions back to external enemies.</content>
  <link name="Base Under Attack!">Continue</link>
</topic>




<topic
  name      = "Base Under Attack!"
  urgent    = "true"
  whenOpen  = "whenBaseAttackTopicOpen"
  completes = "checkDroneAssaultDestroyed"
>
  <content>You asked for it!  Here come two enemy Drones to raze your colony.  Flag them with a Strike Mission ASAP and watch your Troopers handle it.  Don't forget to up the reward.</content>
</topic>

<topic
  name      = "Find The Distant Ruins"
  urgent    = "true"
  triggers  = "checkDroneAssaultDestroyed"
  completes = "checkFarRuinsFound"
>
  <content>Those creatures- known as Artilects- are still a threat, however.  You will need to use Recon Missions to explore the surrounding terrain until you find the Ancient Ruins that spawned the Drones.

(Tip:  Try searching in the same quadrant they came from.)</content>
</topic>

<topic
  name      = "Ruins Discovered"
  urgent    = "true"
  triggers  = "checkFarRuinsFound"
  whenOpen  = "whenFarRuinsFound"
  completes = "checkFarRuinsDestroyed"
  onFinish  = "onFarRuinsDestroyed"
>
  <content>The Ruins have been found.  Now destroy them.</content>
</topic>

<topic
  name      = "Ruins Destroyed"
  urgent    = "true"
  triggers  = "checkFarRuinsDestroyed"
>
  <content>There is one more thing, however.</content>
</topic>



<topic
  name      = "Tutorial Complete"
  urgent    = "true"
  triggers  = "checkTutorialComplete"
>
  <content>Congratulations.</content>
</topic>















